<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of the passion of our Blessed Saviour Jesus Christ preached on Good-Friday, in His Excellencies the Spanish Ambassador's chappel / by J.G., D.D.</title>
            <author>J. G., D.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42525</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G40</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24343</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08141841</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08141841</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40936</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42525)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40936)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1230:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of the passion of our Blessed Saviour Jesus Christ preached on Good-Friday, in His Excellencies the Spanish Ambassador's chappel / by J.G., D.D.</title>
                  <author>J. G., D.D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Matthew Turner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Passion --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Good Friday sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40936:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40936:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON OF THE PASSION Of our Bleſſed SAVIOUR <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preached on <hi>GOOD-FRIDAY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his Excellencies the <hi>SPANISH</hi> Ambaſſador's CHAPPEL.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. G.</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Matthew Turner,</hi> near <hi>Turn-ſtile</hi> in <hi>Holbourn.</hi> 1686.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:40936:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40936:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Calicem quem dedit mihi Pater non bibam illum?</p>
                  <p>The Chalice which my Father hath given me, Shall not I drink it?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <argument>
               <p>Words of the eternal Word made Fleſh, ſpoken to <hi>Peter</hi> in the Garden, when he cut off <hi>Malchus</hi> his Ear, Recorded by St. <hi>John,</hi> in his <hi>18th. Chapter.</hi> &amp;c. And part of the Paſſion read in the Church on <hi>Good-Friday.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>THE Paſſion of our deareſt SAVIOUR is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented unto Us, by His own divine Self, under the notion of a <hi>Chalice,</hi> or draught that was to be Accepted and Swallowed down by the <hi>Perſon</hi> that was to Suffer. <hi>Calicem quem dedit mihi Pater; The Chalice which my father hath given me, ſhall not I drink it?</hi> The ſame Thing as to ſay in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving <hi>Peter</hi> for his forwardneſs without leave or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: The <hi>Paſſion</hi> which my Eternal Father's Will is, I ſhould undergo for thine and all the world's Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wilt thou preſume to put by; Diſpute the Decrees of Heaven, and a Sacrifice to Him ſo acceptable, ſhall I refuſe or neglect to Offer up?</p>
            <p>In the ſame manner had He long before expreſſed His Sufferings; when to Curb and Repreſs the ambitious Thoughts of the Sons of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> who would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with a no leſs humble place, than the Right and the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40936:3"/>Left of the KING of Kings, when ſeated on His Throne; <hi>Dic ut ſedeant hi duo filii mei unus ad dexteram, alter ad ſiniſtram in regno tuo.</hi> He anſwered them, <hi>Poteſtiſne bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere calicem quem ego bibiturus ſum? Can you drink the Chalice which I am about to drink?</hi> Are you ready to Suffer with me? can you imitate my Paſſion? have you both Courage and Will enough to ſhare and partake with me of that heavy Burthen, that my Shoulders ſhall be charg'd withal?</p>
            <p>And in the ſame Sence again, did the Royal Prophet cry out, in the Perſon of ſuch as Suffer'd for Juſtice, <hi>Quid retribuam domino pro omnibus quoe retribuit mihi? Calicem ſalutaris accipiam. What ſhall I retribute to my Lord my God, for all he has confer'd on me? I will em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace his Chalice;</hi> I will make a Return unto Him of all I receiv'd from him, by Offering up my Life unto Him.</p>
            <p>O Bleſſed JESUS, what a <hi>Chalice</hi> haſt Thou choſen to drink for Us? What a bitter Potion has thy FATHER allotted Thee to ſwallow? But, What do I ſay, thy FATHER? It was not He alone that Temper'd and Mixt this Draught for Thee; They were the Sins of Men that gather'd the Ingredients, and made the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound; and yet I muſt ſay, it was His <hi>Father</hi> did it: <hi>Calicem quem dedit mihi Pater; The Chalice that my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gave me, ſhall not I drink it?</hi> The <hi>Father</hi> therefore gave it, and our Sins were the occaſion. Our Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Wickedneſs ſurpaſſing all bounds and meaſure, made the Peparation; the eternal Fathers All-ſurpaſſing Goodneſs and Charity unto Man, lay the injunction for to drink it. <hi>The Chalice which my Father gave me, ſhall not I drink it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will Firſt therefore conſider the Sins of Man, that were the occaſion of this <hi>Chalice;</hi> then the boundleſs Charity of the Eternal FATHER to us Sinners, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40936:3"/>lay the Command of taking it; and from both deſcend to give you a view of the Bitter Ingredients that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded it.</p>
            <p>Miſtake me not, and think this to be the diviſion of my preſent Entertainment; No, no, it is the latter of the Three muſt take up that. This Dayes Diſcourſe muſt be (if not wholly) for the greateſt part of the doleful Sufferings of our Bleeding JESUS. Of the <hi>Affronts,</hi> the <hi>Injuries,</hi> the <hi>Agonies,</hi> the <hi>Pangs</hi> of our Dying SAVIOUR; We muſt caſt our Eyes no other way at preſent, but on a Bloody Sacrifice; and ſuch an one, as was not Conſummated by one ſingle, though Mortal Stroke, as in the Old Law, or amongſt the Heathens; but by a continued Train of the moſt Barbarous Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that Malice it ſelf could ſuggeſt from <hi>Thurſday</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, till <hi>Friday</hi> Three of the Clock in the Afternoon.</p>
            <p>I will ſpeak only a word or two of the Sins that were the occaſion of our Bleſſed SAVIOUR'S Sufferings, that you may not wonder at ſo Heavy a Load, charged on the Shoulders of ſo Innocent a Perſon; and in like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of the divine Charity towards Man-kind, to raiſe a Gratitude in your Souls, anſwering the Love of a <hi>Father,</hi> that could lay ſuch a Command on ſuch a Son; and the Love of a Son, that could Embrace ſo readily, and Execute ſo effectually, ſuch a Command of a <hi>Father. Calicem quem dedit mihi Pater, non bibam illum? The Chalice which my Father gave me, ſhall not I drink it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Conſideration of the Sins of Men, ſhall compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, Firſt the number of them, if to be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and then their Foulneſs.</p>
            <p>As to the number of the Sins of Men, it is a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Account to think on. From the Fall of our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, which opened the Gate to Sin, to the viſible Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the SAVIOUR of the World, many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40936:4"/>Years were Elapſed; numberleſs their Iſſue, yet none of all thoſe, except particularly Priviledg'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sin: Beſides the greateſt part; nay, the far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part <hi>Idolaters,</hi> ignorant of their Creator, trained up from their Infancy, in all ſorts of infamous and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Practiſes, and ſo continuing to their end.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe, who had the Bleſſing to be Inſtructed in the Knowledge of one <hi>Deity,</hi> infinite in himſelf, and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Heaven and Earth, either before or after the Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Law; ſuch was the Corruption of their manners, ſo great, ſo general, and ſo frequent their Defection from Orders given them, and the Dictates of their own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that they came but little ſhort of the others.</p>
            <p>The Sins of us Chriſtians I dare not name before you, it is the higheſt confuſion unto me to think there ſhould be any: Yet I muſt tell you, we are none of us without them, and ſo common amongſt us, that we ſee them in the Streets; ſee them within our Doors; meet with them in Publick; meet with them in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate; they flie not the ſhame of the open Aire, and every corner ſeems throng'd with them: if I may not ſay, they are as numerous as before the coming of our Redeemer; I will ſay, and boldly ſay, they are much more Foul and Inexcuſable.</p>
            <p>Which Foulneſs of Sin in general, is my other conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; and truly worthy not a Moment, Hour, or Dayes Reflection; for our whole life, tho' never ſo long, and full of Dayes, muſt be too ſhort to enter into a juſt meditation of it; ſo Diſmal and ſo Dark is its Nature; ſo Venemous, ſo Outragious its Effects.</p>
            <p>It ſpoiles and diſrobes the Soul, tho' by Nature an Excellent Creature, and by Grace a Singular Favorite of the <hi>Deity;</hi> Of all its Beauty, all its Sanctity, all its Innocence: it makes it appear in the Eyes of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40936:4"/>moſt Ugly, moſt Deformed, moſt Contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. It robs the Soul of the Bleſſed Inheritance of Heaven; and in lieu of that, ſecures it of the juſt Wrath and Anger of his offended God. In a Word, the proper effect of Sin, is to render the Soul like unto its ſelf, which being really nothing; for Whatſoever can chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the notion of a thing, was made by the Creator of all things; makes the Soul appear alſo as nothing. Nothing in the Sight of God, nothing in his Favour, nothing in his Good Will, nothing in Deſert, nothing in any Right, by which it can juſtly challenge either Natural, or Supernatural Good.</p>
            <p>A Monſter I may call it, for Man wrongs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts the courſe of Nature, as often as he ſins; and a Monſter of that Malignity, as can hardly find its equal. For ſuch is its Primogeneous and innate Poiſon, that it certainly deſtroys the Creature that gives it being; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing under a rational Creature by nature can be Author of a Sin; and at the ſame time he ſinneth, he muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his reaſon.</p>
            <p>One only quality it has that can ſound commendable, and even that augments the miſery of Man; that is, to be of its own nature eternal; for did not the Divine Mercy interpoſe, whoſoever ſinneth, would be a Slave unto his ſin for ever: But Bleſſed for ever and ever, be the Goodneſs of the Eternal Father, who ſo loved the World, that he would ſend, and not only ſend into the World his Son to be charged with all thoſe Sins you have heard me ſpeak of; but to take upon himſelf the cancelling of them all: And Bleſſed, I ſay, Bleſſed for ever be the Goodneſs of his Son, who would come into this World, and give even the laſt drop of his Blod for Mans Redemption.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:40936:5"/>
            <p>After the infinity of the Divine Nature, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible excellencies within himſelf, I can find no other ground for the immenſity of the Divine Charity towards his ſinful Creatures, than the number, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Sins: for could the Divine Charity have been bounded with Limits, the Sins of Man had certainly ſurpaſs'd it; but far be it from the God we Chriſtians adore, to have his Goodneſs, his Bounty ſo contracted, as to be equall'd or ſurmounted by the Malice, by the Sins, tho' almoſt Infinite, of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>Man's Sins were of themſelves able to make him deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate; the deſperateneſs of his Condition touched unto the quick, if I may ſo expreſs it; the Bowels of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Goodneſs, and that Goodneſs ſent us a Redeemer. This Redeemer being come into this World amongſt Men, waged War with Sin, and at laſt overcame it in his own Perſon, tho' it coſt him dear. Without Drinking the bitter Cup of his Paſſion it was not to be done; and from that, neither <hi>Peters</hi> Kindneſs, nor any other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive could keep him back. <hi>Calicem quem dedit mihi Pater non bibam illum? The Chalice which my Father hath given me, ſhall not I Drink it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hadſt thou not Bleſſed JESUS, ſignified a diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction or diſpleaſure at <hi>Peters</hi> forwardneſs to defend Thee, in my Wiſhes I ſhould have joyn'd with <hi>Peter.</hi> Should I not be unjuſt unto all Mankind, who were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers and ſharers of the bleſſings of thy Paſſion; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unjuſt to thy Divine Charity, which made the brighteſt, and moſt radiant diſcovery of it ſelf unto the world, that it was capable of receiving? what is there I would not have done or ſuffered to prevent the drinking of thy <hi>Chalice?</hi> But I am frighted! dare neither ſpeak nor wiſh! Thy reprehenſion of bleſſed <hi>Peter</hi> is alwayes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40936:5"/>ſounding in my ears: <hi>The Chalice which my Father hath given me, ſhall not I drink it?</hi> Yes, bleſſed JESUS, drink it, comply with thy Fathers order; but teach us to do the like.</p>
            <p>Well, the Reſolution is taken; the <hi>Chalice</hi> he will drink, though never ſo bitter; his ardent Charity has vanquiſht and put to flight all reſiſtances, all oppoſitions that interven'd betwixt him and his Croſs. He has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to act; he muſt be wholly paſſive: ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and the moſt grievous of all ſufferings are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients of his <hi>Chalice;</hi> which I will take apart, that you may conſider them the better: As a diſſection in a ſolid body, ſo diviſion and taking apart the ingredients in others, makes the perfecteſt diſcovery. I will let you ſee</p>
            <list>
               <item>What he Suffered in the garden of <hi>Gethſemani.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What in the hands of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What from the power of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Again,</p>
            <list>
               <item>What from Himſelf.</item>
               <item>What from his Countrymen.</item>
               <item>What from Aliens and Strangers to his Nation.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In a word, the diviſion of my Diſcourſe ſhall be the diviſion of his Paſſion.</p>
            <list>
               <item>In the 1ſt. part I will lay before you,
<list>
                     <item>What he ſuffer'd precedently to his ſeizure by his Enemies the <hi>Jewes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>In my 2d.
<list>
                     <item>What He ſuffered from them.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>In my 3d.
<list>
                     <item>What from the power and command of the <hi>Roman</hi> Governour.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>What he ſuffer'd precedently to his Seizure by the <hi>Jews,</hi> may be reduced to theſe <hi>Three</hi> Heads.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40936:6"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>His ſufferings from his Diſciples.</item>
                     <item>From his Father.</item>
                     <item>From Himſelf.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>All bitter ſufferings, becauſe from Friends; from ſuch as he loved dearly. That he loved his Diſciples, you will not queſtion. His choice of them, to be partakers of all his Traverſees here, to be ſharers with him of his Adverſity and Proſperity, abundantly demonſtrate.</p>
            <p>That he loved his Father, muſt be more undoubted, of whom, though infinite in himſelf, he received all his being; and to whom he had alwayes payed all the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he could Reverence him withall.</p>
            <p>From the Treachery of a Diſciple, his Paſſion was to commence; <hi>Amen, dico vobis unus veſtrum me traditurus eſt. Amen, I ſay unto you, one of you is about to betray me.</hi> And whether is this Treachery to be? What does it ſtrike at? Where will be its end? Betray him into the hands of cruel and blood-ſucking Enemies. Into the Hands of ſuch as thirſt after his Life, there it ſtrikes: And who will never reſt content untill they have it; there it ends.</p>
            <p>The manner of this Treachery alſo involves ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of Ingratitude and Villany, as can hardly be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed; for it was meditating and acting in the very inſtant that our Bleſſed <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> was preparing a Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet; Nay, What, do I ſay a Banquet? when he was laying up a Kingdom for him.</p>
            <p>The token by which it was to be executed, was a <hi>Kiſs; Quemcunquoe oſculatus fuero, ipſe eſt tenete eum. Whomſoever I ſhall kiſs, he it is, lay hands on him, and hold him faſt.</hi> Hold him faſt! Blind and Perfidious Traytor! Knoweſt thou not he is not to be held, but by his own free will? Canſt thou ſo ſoon forget how at other times his Enemies had no power over him, becauſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40936:6"/>he would not? or, Seeſt thou not now, how all thy Armed Bands lye proſtrate at his Feet, at the very opening of his Mouth?</p>
            <p>The unworthineſs of this Action was ſuch, to make uſe of the higheſt Token of Friendſhip, of the very Seal of Peace, to Betray the Beſt of Friends, to Commence open War withal, could not but move the Heart of the mildeſt of Lambs, and draw from Him this gentle Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulation; <hi>Juda oſculo filium hominis tradis? Judas,</hi> (My old Diſciple, my Boſome Friend, who wert daily Riſing and Lying down with Me: I bury in Silence what I have done More for thee) <hi>Doeſt thou betray me with a Kiſs?</hi> Canſt thou be ſo Deceitful, as to make uſe of the higheſt Token of Endearment, to expreſs the Blackeſt Malice, and Vomit out thy Poyſon?</p>
            <p>From the Infidelity again of a Diſciple, in the midſt of His Diſtreſs, when the owning, at leaſt of a Friend, might have afforded Him ſome ſmall Comfort; Is his Paſſion carried on, by a flat Denial; nay, Forſwearing of any, though the leaſt Acquaintance. <hi>Coepit deteſtari &amp; jurare quia non noviſſet hominem.</hi> From the Tepidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Negligence of altogether, in the Garden of <hi>Geth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemani,</hi> was he deſerted, and left alone, void of all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, ſeparate from all Friends; deſolate, diſtreſſed, and forlorn.</p>
            <p>Such as ſhould have Born up with Him, Confronted all his Dangers, and hazarded (a Man would have thought) their ſmall Fortunes for Him: Leave Him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in the open Air, dark Night, and already Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling at the Approach of thoſe, into whoſe Hands He was immediately to Fall. They unconcern'd betake themſelves to Reſt, Indulge their heavy Humours; and ſome of them, though twice deſired (by their <hi>Maſter</hi>) for to Watch, ſtill yield themſelves up to Sleep and Reſt.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40936:7"/>
               <hi>Non potuiſtis una hora vigilare mecum?</hi> Well may He Reproach us all here preſent, with the ſame Expreſſion, <hi>Non potuiſtis una hora vigilare mecum? Could not you watch one hour with me.</hi> You all know the Concern of Watching; your Enemy is vigilant; <hi>Circuit quoerens quem devoret,</hi> (ſayes St. <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>He takes his rounds to find whom he may devour;</hi> and for want of vigilancy in you, has he ſo often ſurpriz'd you, and drawn you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sin. Want of Vigilancy has been the cauſe of all your Treacheries, all your Denials, all your Neglects of my Commandements: Had you Watched when you ought, you had never Betrayed Me like to <hi>Judas,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied Me like <hi>Peter,</hi> nor Quitted and Deſerted Me like the reſt of my Diſciples, whoſe Treachery, Denial, and ſupine Negligence, are the beginning of theſe my Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and make up the Doleful Entry of my Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>That He Suffered, and grievouſly Suffer'd from his FATHER, His beloved FATHER, we ſhall not need to ſeek far to find: What ſayes the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> St. <hi>John? Calicem quem dedit mihi Pater, non vis ut bibam illum; The Chalice that my Father hath given me, ſhall not I drink it?</hi> His Father therefore prepared his Bitter <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice</hi> for Him? His <hi>Father</hi> lay the Injunction for to drink it. <hi>Calicem quem dedit mihi Pater; The Chalice which my Father hath given me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, we found out the Matter, Our Sins, our Tranſgreſſions, our Wickedneſs were the occaſion; But it was the Eternal FATHER'S Goodneſs towards His Adopted but Rebellious Children, that made Him be ſo Severe unto His Son, that ſent Him into this World, and here laid unto His Charge, whatſoever the former were guilty of; and which could not be diſcharged, without His drinking of the <hi>Chalice. Calicem quem dedit mihi
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40936:7"/>Pater, non vis ut bibam illum?</hi> But, What need of exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> about the Point in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, if there be any ſuch? The Words of our deareſt JESUS in the Garden of <hi>Gethſemani,</hi> will make all as clear as Noon-day. What was his Prayer unto Heaven, when he parted a Stones caſt from His choſen Diſciples, which He left Poſted at that diſtance? What, I ſay, was his Prayer, but <hi>Pater ſi poſſibile eſt, tranſeat a me calix iſte; Father,</hi> (deareſt FATHER, whom I never yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed, whoſe Will has been alwayes Mine) <hi>if it be poſſible, let this Chalice paſs from me;</hi> Lay not ſo heavy a Command on the Shoulders of Thy loving Son: Let not thy Anger exert it ſelf againſt my innocence. I know, deareſt FATHER, Thou haſt ordered it, but are Thy Decrees alwayes immutable like thy Self? No, no, I remember thy Threats, thy Menaces renverſed upon Juſt Reaſons; and, why not, at the Petition, at the earneſt Requeſt of thy moſt Dutiful, and moſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant Son; <hi>If it be poſſible, let this Chalice paſs from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this was his Prayer to his <hi>Father,</hi> if thus He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired unto Him to be Relieved from that Anguiſh, which began already to Rage within Him, to be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, and Defended from that Storm, which was juſt diſcharging its ſelf upon his Head; it muſt be his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>'s Anger and Severity He lay under, and His Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings be the greater, that they were from ſuch a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Undoubtedly it was grievous to Suffer from Friends, and ſuch were his Diſciples: More grievous to Suffer from a <hi>Father,</hi> and ſo Dear a <hi>Father;</hi> but to Suffer from Himſelf, muſt needs exceed all other Sufferings, if that be once made out, and nothing is more eaſy, by a plain Convincing reaſon; and by the dire effects which were
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40936:8"/>ſo terrible, and ſo ſurpaſſing all Belief, if not delivered by an infallible Oracle; that whatſoever the <hi>Jews,</hi> the <hi>Gentiles</hi> caſt after on Him, of Reproach, Scorn, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, bodily Affliction, and the like, ſeem but trifles in compariſon of them.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon, by which I promiſed to Convince you of our <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> Suffering, and unexpreſſible Suffering from Himſelf, I draw from the nature of our Fancy, whoſe Operation is ſo powerful and quick upon the Body, that, in an inſtant, I may ſay, it influences the very utmoſt, and remoteſt Parts: We no ſooner appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what is pleaſing and agreeable to our Humour, but we become all over lightſom, and every Part of us ſhares of the Joy. No ſooner, on the contrary, is our Fancy poſſeſt with the Apprehenſion of what is noxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and prejudicial, but, in a moment, all our Mirth is daſhed, our Joyes flie from us, we become Lumpiſh, Heavy, and Diſtracted: Nay, ſometimes the power and faculty of Motion, is by a ſecret Damp, either for the preſent ſeized, or for ever withdrawn.</p>
            <p>And if this be the daily Experience of us all, upon airy and volatile Apprehenſions of good and evil; what muſt be the Operations of our Bleſſed <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi>'s Fancy, where fully, at large, and to the life, were ſet forth, all the ignominious Treatments, all the Painful and Dolorous Expreſſions of Malice in his Perſon, all the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in a word. His ſacred Body was to run thorow, during the whole Courſe of his Paſſion, even to His ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring on the Croſs.</p>
            <p>Nay, which is yet more, and which workt on him more, all the Sins of unthankful Chriſtians, all their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, all their Neglects, and wilful Omiſſions of improving their Souls by thoſe his voluntary Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:40936:8"/>
            <p>I may ask the queſtion, How ſtrong, how violent, how forcing on the Body muſt ſuch a Fancy be, but none but He can anſwer it? So much did it exceed all our Apprehenſions, that we muſt come infinitely ſhort of the Truth, had there not been a conſiderable Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very made by the Effects; which, as the Evangeliſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them, I will expoſe to your conſideration.</p>
            <p>When the Paſſion grows ſo ſtrong upon us, that with difficulty it is kept in, a fear or ſadneſs of Mind (for example, Expreſſes it ſelf in outward Action, in change or alteration of Body;) it is a certain ſign, an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Argument, it touches to the Quick, ſeizes on the Spirit, begins to daunt and baffle our natural Courage, which, in our Bleſſed SAVIOUR, had been always ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary in the midſt of dangers, in the throng of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties. At preſent notwithſtanding, ſo far is He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed upon; ſo much did the Apprehenſion of what was to follow, work upon Him, that He found a real Change within Him. I will not ſay, his Fortitude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to leave him, far be it from me to have any ſuch Thought; for that remain'd unſhaken, till He expir'd on the Croſs; but his inferiour Part began to expreſs an inward Anguiſh, and a violent Oppreſſion of thoſe Spirits, which had hitherto made him appear alwayes Inaltera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his Humour and Conſtitution. <hi>Coepit contriſtari,</hi> ſayes St. <hi>Matthew, &amp; moeſtus eſſe; He began to be ſad, and very much dejected.</hi> Nor was this all, for every Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment encreaſing, it came to ſuch a pitch, that Death could not be bitterer? He gives us the Expreſſion him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; <hi>Triſtis eſt anima mea uſque ad mortem; My Soul is ſad, even unto Death.</hi> The Acerbity of my Anguiſh pinches me ſo, as the violent Pangs of <hi>Death</hi> could do no more.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> I believe Thee, it was not for nothing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40936:9"/>the Angel came from Heaven to Comfort thee. <hi>Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uit autem illi angelus de coelo confortans eum.</hi> There was need enough of it, thy Soul was ſo ſtreightned: Such Ebullitions and Æſtuations in thy Blood, that its Veins are not able to hold it longer; it muſt force its way; and were there Walls of Braſs or Iron, they could not keep it within its Channels. <hi>Et factus eſt ſudor ejus ſicut guttoe ſanguinis decurrentis in terram; And his Sweat became like to drops of Blood falling on the ground.</hi> Let the cauſe of it be either exceſs of Fear, or the fortitude of his Mind endeavouring to repreſs it, 'tis all one with me, I am ſure his Pains were never the leſs. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Conflict that could force from him ſuch a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of Blood, muſt ſo reverſe and undermine the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of his Conſtitution, that nothing leſs than the Hand of the Almighty, could have Supported him after ſuch a Sweat, and given him ſtrength to go through one quarter of the difficulties he was ſpeedily to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I ſay ſpeedily; for, behold the Traitor <hi>Judas</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the Garden, at the Head of a band of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, Marching up towards Him with Swords, Clubs, and other ſuch like Inſtruments, as they could, with ſpeed, gather up to Secure our <hi>Sampſon,</hi> whoſe Dalila, that is his Love, had already diſarmed, and diſabled from making a Defence. <hi>Ecce Judas unus de duodecim venit, &amp; cum eo turba multa cum gladiis &amp; fuſtibus.</hi> So that it is not long before they Seize him; before they lay violent hands upon him: <hi>Tunc acceſſerunt, &amp; manus injecerunt in Jeſum &amp; tenuerunt eum; Then they came near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, caſt their hands on Jeſus, and held him faſt.</hi> And his Sufferings there make up the ſecond part of that Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy I promiſed to Repreſent unto you at this preſent time; and which, becauſe I will continue my former Method, I will diſtinguiſh alſo into parts,</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40936:9"/>
            <list>
               <item>What He Suffered before his Condemnation.</item>
               <item>What by His Condemnation it ſelf.</item>
               <item>What after.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Before his Condemnation was, the whole Treatment he received from <hi>Judas</hi> his Band of Cut-Throats, as he was hurrying along to the Pallaces of <hi>Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiphas;</hi> as likewiſe in their Houſes, by Violence on his Perſon, and Infamy of Falſe-Witneſſes, before the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Death paſt on him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judas</hi> had given them a Caution to <hi>hold him faſt;</hi> and therefore, no ſooner had they Seized him, but with Cords and Ropes, they bound his Hands, and with ſuch force drew them both together, that no ſmall impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions they Engraved on his tender Fleſh; His ſacred Feet they loaded not with Irons, but, For what reaſon, out of mercy or tenderneſs to his Perſon? Nothing leſs. It was their Malice, that they might, with greater ſpeed, bring Him before his New-Erected Judges, ſooner to his Trial, with more Expedition to his End. And therefore, inſtead of giving their New-made Priſoner leave to walk ſoberly in their company, with other Ropes, about Neck and Body, they Forced him along, with much more Haſt and Violence, than could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for ſuch a Priſoner, as had not the uſe of one Hand left him, to Raiſe him up again, in caſe he ſhould ſtumble in the Way.</p>
            <p>'Tis not long before He arrived at the Houſe of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> Father-in-Law to <hi>Caiphas,</hi> High-Prieſt of that year, whether they firſt conducted Him, both by reaſon his Houſe was in the way, and that he was a conſiderable Perſon, as appears by his ſo near Alliance with the High-Prieſt: Where, though we read but little Acted; 'tis not to be doubted, but his Pride and Arrogance, drew from him many Impertinent, if not Impious Queſtions: And
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40936:10"/>the Inſolence of the Rabble continuing, or rather every moment Increaſing, they heaped on Him Injuries an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to what the Holy Scriptures relate, to have been afterwards expreſſed from their Malice. But the Seniors of the People, together with the Scribes, being Aſſembled at the High-Prieſts Pallace, He was ſoon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched thither. <hi>Et miſit eum</hi> Annas <hi>ligatum ad</hi> Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pham <hi>pontificem; And</hi> Annas <hi>ſent him bound to</hi> Caiphas <hi>the High-Prieſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where He might juſtly expect all Illegal and Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable Proceeding from theſe following Reaſons. Firſt of all it was <hi>Caiphas,</hi> at whoſe Bar He muſt now ſtand that Propheſied his Death. 2ly. It was he that perſwaded them to Seize Him, and put Him to Death. 3ly. It was at his Houſe, where all the Princes of the Prieſts, with the Antients of the People were Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and on deſign Aſſembled, to uſe all ſort of deceit, and fraudulent wayes; both to lay Hold of Him, and make Him away. <hi>Et concilium fecerunt,</hi> ſayes St. Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, <hi>ut Jeſum dolo tenerent &amp; occiderent.</hi> 4ly. They had Bought Him of the Traitor <hi>Judas,</hi> though they had nothing of Truth to lay unto his Charge. And Laſtly, They let Him ſtill remain in the hands of the Rabble, whoſe Barbarity was ſuch, that nothing wanted Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that came but into their Fancies, though the moſt brutiſh, and tranſcendently unnatural Violences.</p>
            <p>And as He might juſtly expect the height of Illega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and Violence from the Precedent Heads, ſo he met with all in the height. He failed not of his Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the leaſt; His uſage was beyond all parallel.</p>
            <p>As nothing of Injuſtice and Invention was wanting in the High-Prieſt, and thoſe of his diabolical Council; ſo nothing of Baſeneſs and Abuſiveneſs, was omitted by his <hi>Black-Guard,</hi> and ſuch as every Moment flocked
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40936:10"/>thither, to be either Spectators, or Sharers in his Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and Trial.</p>
            <p>The High-Prieſt, ſitting as Judge, and Paramount a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the reſt, ſwelling with Pride, as well he might, undertaking to Judge the JUDGE of the World; firſt askt Him queſtions about his Diſciples, and concerning his Doctrine. <hi>Pontifex ergo,</hi> ſayes St. <hi>John, interrogavit Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum de Diſcipulis ſuis, &amp; de doctrina ejus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But finding not his Advantage there; for, What could he draw from the Mouth of Truth, whoſe Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was deſignedly to be built up of lies and falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? Blind he was to perſonate Authority; to uſurp upon Innocence, and Him that had all Power in His Hands, if He had pleaſed to make uſe of it; but not ſo blind, as to think he could gain any thing upon the anſwer of his Priſoner; and therefore, betakes himſelf to the only means applicable in ſuch caſes; <hi>Falſities, Lies, Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, Perjuries,</hi> and the like: Falſe Witneſſes muſt be brought; their Allegations muſt be taken; their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies muſt run current; their Oaths unqueſtionable; the pretended truth of what they delivered, lookt on as ſacred; by no contrary Evidence diſputed, and abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſufficient to Found a Sentence; nay, a ſentence of Death on. <hi>Principes autem ſacerdotum &amp; omne concilium querebant falſum teſtimonium contra Jeſum, ut eum morti traderant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Bleſſed JESUS! How is thy Life ſearcht after! How is thy Innocence traduced! How do thy Enemies now vomit forth their Malice! For, What greater Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice can there be, than knowingly and wittingly to make uſe of the blackeſt and fouleſt of Means, for the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Innocence it ſelf? Had He been a Malefactor, or open Enemy to their Nation, there were Eyes enough
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40936:11"/>to have diſcovered it, and no Will wanting to have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd and made it known: But there is no ſuch thing as yet alledged, Falſe Witneſſes muſt do the turn, if poſſible, for True ones, they are not to be found; none in being, and ſo not to be Subpoened in: Yet Die He muſt, Guilty He is; and ſince that <hi>Judas</hi> has received Mony for Him, he muſt not Eſcape his doom. To Evidencing therefore they go; upon Interrogatories they make their Anſwers: But, upon a ſuddain, all their Deſigns are crampt; all their Endeavours blaſted; all their Hopes are daſhed. For, ſo little care had been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in their Inſtructions; ſo ſmall regard of an Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in their Leſſons, that, what one Aſſerted, the other Contradicted; what one Avouched, a ſecond poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Denied. <hi>Multi enim teſtimonium falſum dicebant adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eum, &amp; convenientia teſtimonia non erant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At which, the Judge enraged, no leſs unreaſonably, than impertinently, demands of his Priſoner at the Bar, Why He made no Anſwer to what was alledged againſt Him? Whereas, indeed, there was nothing to anſwer to: For, if the Witneſſes agree not; if there be jarring in the Teſtimony given, the Accuſation falls of it ſelf, and ſtands for nothing. Make therefore firſt thy Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes agree proud Prieſt, and then make thy Demand; then make uſe of that, thy Confidence in asking Him, Why he Anſwers nothing: But the occaſion is now loſt; the Opportunity, even of a ſhadow-like Conviction is let ſlip, and their Cauſe muſt fall, if our JESUS him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf will not advance one ſtep towards it; and rather than be cleared, He will advance much father; for the <hi>Chalice</hi> his <hi>Father</hi> gave Him, muſt not paſs without his drinking it. <hi>Calicem quem dedit mihi, non bibam il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:40936:11"/>
            <p>His Reply to the High-Prieſts following queſtion, and laſt refuge, put them all at Eaſe; for fretting within himſelf, and ſeeing nothing would prevail, he falls again upon his Interrogatories; and with his <hi>Adjuro te per Deum vivum ut dicas nobis ſi tu es Chriſtus filius Dei; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure thee by the living God, that thou tell us, if thou art Chriſt the Son of God:</hi> Drew from our Bleſſed JESUS, that <hi>Tu dixiſti, Thou haſt ſaid it;</hi> which put an end to all their ſollicitude and doubts; freed them of all their cares and fears of his Eſcape; occaſion'd the High-Prieſts rending of his Garments; made him preſently Guilty of Blaſphemy, in his Judgment; and Blaſphemy deſerved Death, according to the Law. Whereupon, the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is pronounced by the Voice of the whole Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, Crying out, <hi>Reus eſt mortis, He is guilty of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He now ſtands a Condemned Perſon, and Affronts will ſoon be redoubled on Him: If, before his Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a ſtander by, in preſence of the Judge, and face of the whole Court, could be ſo Inſolent, as to ſtrike Him over his divine Countenance, without the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premand; I wonder not, if they think all Things law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful afterwards. A Summary I will give you, and the beſt Account I am able of their Indignities, Villanies, and furious Aſſaults on his ſacred Perſon, after a word or two, of that ſo unjuſt, illegal, and precipitated Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            <p>As nothing, in this world, can be dearer to us, than our Lives, nothing in equal value with our Being; ſo nothing can be equally injurious, equally pernitious, with what robs us of our Being, bereaves us of our Lives. From whence, every unjuſt Sentence unto Death, let it be by what ſiniſter means ſoever, it values not, is the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40936:12"/>higheſt of Injuries, the moſt execrable of Malices, the blackeſt of Inhumanities: And that, in this Sentence, whatſoever could render it Juſt was wanting, nothing can be more evident: For the Judge was wholly void of authority over the Perſon Condemned; no Crime made out againſt the Priſoner; all Witneſſes Suborn'd and Perjur'd; and even thoſe not agreeing in their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, and Judgment given by the Accuſers and the Rabble. Well then may it be aſſerted, That our SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIOUR'S Sufferings, in his Condemnation, were very grievous, and beyond Expreſſion.</p>
            <p>To conceive it ſomthing better, pray imagine with your ſelves, any private Perſon Uſurping ſuch Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over his Neighbour, as upon preſumption of his own Intereſt, Will, or Pleaſure, ſhould force or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel him to the place of Execution, and there Throttle him with a Halter, Cut his Throat, or the like: You will take that Man to be a very great Sufferer in the caſe, and the Execution to be a heinous, nay, helliſh Action: Yet 'tis no more, than every unjuſt Sentence unto death; nor is the Perſon ſo Condemned, a leſs Sufferer: For, 'tis all one and the ſame thing to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn to Death, and effectually Rob one of his Life; and he that gives the Sentence in his Chair, turns the Ladder, and gives the Blow with the Executioner, in the place, whither the pretended Criminal is brought to Suffer.</p>
            <p>But what need I uſe ſo many words about his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering in his Condemnation: You are ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the enormity of the Action, of the foulneſs of the Injury; and therefore, I will now go on, and ſee what paſſed after.</p>
            <p>The Evangeliſt St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40936:12"/>both relate the Injuries; neither of them, all, nor both together, all; yet both enough to imprint in us a Senſe, if we be not paſt all Senſe, of that diſmal Night, in which the Light of the World was Ecclips't; the Beauty of Heaven defiled; Innocence it ſelf mockt and derided; Patience exceeding all its common notions, born down and trampled on.</p>
            <p>I will begin with that Divine Face, on which the Angels deſire to look; and which was ſo coveted by the Antient Patriarcks, that they longed after it, as the fulneſs of Happineſs. <hi>Oſtende faciem tuam &amp; ſalvi erimus.</hi> This ſame Countenance, tho' never ſo reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lendent in its ſelf; tho' the ſeat of all excellencies and graces, are they ſo unmannerly and dirty, as to load with their filthy ſpittle: <hi>Tunc expuerunt in faciem ejus.</hi> Of what others from whom Modeſty is not wholly baniſht, ſearch for corners and private holes to diſcharge their ſtomacks do they make his Face, his Bleſſed Face the common receptacle and ſink; which when all fouled by their ordures and filthyneſs, and become an unfit ſpectacle to the World, they cover with ſome beaſtly or naſty clout, that he might not ſee the injuries they were reſolved to heap upon him after: But alas, they are blind, not He; They ſee not what they do, when with ſuch outrages they aſſault the Lamb of God, and conteſt who ſhall abuſe him moſt, who ſhall ſhew moſt wit, and forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in adding to the Calamities of our now helpleſs SAVIOUR.</p>
            <p>Blind then as they are, do they load his Head with blows; his Cheeks do they pull and buffet, &amp; at the ſame time illuding him with Mockeries, and inſulting with Rudeneſs, cry out, <hi>Propheſie unto us CHRIST, who it was that ſtroke thee. Tunc expuerunt in faciem ejus, &amp;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40936:13"/>colaphis eum ceciderunt. Alii autem palmas in faciem ejus dederunt, dicentes prophetiza nobis Chriſte, quis eſt qui te percuſſit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Devout Peruſers of the Particulars of our SAVIOURS Paſſion, and ſuch as delight with the fulleſt draught of his Sufferings, enquire about the difference between buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting with Cuffs, &amp; ſtrokes with the palms of the Hands; both which are expreſſed by the Evangeliſt in our Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering-JESUS preſent treatment: And they reſolve Buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting to be by clinched fiſts, when fingers are drawn up together to render the Blow more violent and pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating; and thoſe they diſcharged with all fury on his Head; whereas with palms, is the ſame, as with ſtrecht<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fingers, and with thoſe they ſpared not his Cheeks: So that what between the one and the other, we may conclude both Head and Face, with thoſe violent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſions, not only ſore to extremity, but even ſwoln to admiration.</p>
            <p>Whilſt their Hands were ſo buſie, you may be ſure their Tongues were not ſilent; but on the contrary, reſtleſs in vomiting out all manner of Calumnies, nay, even Blaſphemies againſt his Sacred Perſon: They were ſo ungrateful, or rather ſo ungodly, as to exprobate and reproach him of his former Actions of Goodneſs and Charity, of which he had bin ſo profuſe amongſt them. The Evangeliſts bury moſt of their expreſſions in ſilence; but to aſſure us that ſuch paſſed, and alſo in abundance, St. <hi>Luke</hi> commends to poſterity theſe words: <hi>Et alia multa Blaſphemantes dicebant in eum: And Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming they ſpoke many other things againſt Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Night thus paſſing in Abuſes from the ſcum and dreggs of the People, without any reſt or quiet, tho' for a moment altogether tyred and weary, early in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40936:13"/>Morning is he preſented again unto the Council, which confirming by a ſecond Condemnation what had paſſed over night; he is again bound, and preſently diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away, with the whole multitude of People attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ready to run him down with their numbers, if their Judgment ſhould be call'd in Queſtion by the <hi>Roman</hi> Governour; for they delivered him unto <hi>Pilate</hi> only to ſee and order Execution; not to examine, or make inſpection into their Sentence, as St. <hi>Leo</hi> obſerves in his eighth Sermon on the Paſſion.</p>
            <p>O Bleſſed Jeſus! How art thou hurried from one place to another! from <hi>Annas</hi> to <hi>Caiphas!</hi> From him again to <hi>Pilate!</hi> Firſt into the hands of thy People the <hi>Jewes,</hi> now from them again into the hands of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigners; of Strangers to thy Nation, and who allwayes regarded them as a tumultuous and headſtrong People: So that little mercy can be expected now. If thy own People have been ſo Cruel, what can be hoped from a People whoſe Education and Principles ſavour'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of gentleneſs, nothing but roughneſs, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</p>
            <p>He is now in the hands of <hi>Pilate,</hi> and only remains to ſee what was done by him, by whoſe Order was acted the laſt; and withall, the moſt Cruel and Bloody part of all the Tragedy. So that pray arm your ſelves with patience now to hear a piece of Cruelty, Infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Villany that ſurpaſſes all degrees of moderation; ſuch as neither former dayes have, nor poſterity ſhall repreſent the like: Such as are able to ſoften hearts moulded of Flint or Steel, and ſuch as an ocean of Tears will not evidence a ſufficient and anſwering reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>When you have heard them, I know your hearts
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40936:14"/>will work. I will therefore particularize theſe laſt and mortal Suffering of our SAVIOUR; by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering</p>
            <list>
               <item>What He Suffer'd whilſt in the hands of <hi>Pontius Pilate.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What from the <hi>Roman</hi> Souldiers.</item>
               <item>What upon the Croſs.</item>
            </list>
            <p>'Tis true, the <hi>Roman</hi> Governour ſcrupled at the firſt to execute what they preſſed; he ſeemed backward to inflict the ultimate of Diſgraces and Torments on a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of whoſe Faultineſs he was no wayes convinced; and therefore not only beg'd their excuſe, till he had thorowly examin'd his Guiltineſs, and approved his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merits; but moreover, ſtuck not to declare him Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and Guiltleſs upon Examination; that he found no cauſe of death, nor ſuch their deadly malice, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would diſmiſs him. <hi>Ego nullam invenio in eo cauſam mortis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he wanting courage to perſiſt unto the end, their cries ſounding and redoubling in the Air; their impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities every moment increaſing; their inſtances, their demands urged and repeated, weaken his Reſolutions, invalidate his firſt purpoſes, make him dubious and thoughtful what to do. Howſoever, he will make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, if by any means they may be drawn from that their violent way of proceeding, and by cunning diſarm'd of their malicious intentions; and therefore asks them which they would have freed, <hi>Barabbas</hi> an infamous Murtherer, or JESUS, whom they had lately committed to his cuſtody, as the cuſtom was to ſet one free, whom they ſhould demand on ſuch Feſtival times; with exactneſs he examined all their Accuſation, diſcover'd it; a whole Fabrick of Malice of the Prieſt and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40936:14"/>Ancients, built upon the eaſineſs of the common People; could find not the leaſt plauſible ground for a well-laid Accuſation; and therefore, with diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, could believe they ſhould be ſo ſhameleſs, as to prefer the moſt noted, and blaſted of Malefactors, before the mildeſt and moſt Innocent of Priſoners. But he miſt in his deſign, his project took no effect; for having now ſo long run on beyond the bounds of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, honour and conſcience, they ſtick not to petition the diſcharge of <hi>Barabbas;</hi> and tremble not with brazen Faces, to reiterate their impious Poſtulations of having JESUS to be Crucified, <hi>At illi magis clamabant dicentes Crucifigatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed and deareſt JESUS! What paſs art Thou now come to? or rather, to what degree of Impiety and Ingratitude are theſe thy People arrived? Thee, the true SAVIOUR of Mankind; the true Deliverer of thy People from the endleſs Slavery of the infernal Tyrant; they Chooſe and pre-Elect to Torments, to the Death of the Croſs, by preferring a Thief, a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, and vileſt of Malefactors before Thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pilate</hi> is not yet quite diſcouraged, he has one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention more; he would do Him a Pleaſure, but mixt with ſo much Gall, that I leave you to judge, whether the Remedy be preferable to the Diſeaſe. He will endeavour to Mollifie their ſtubborn Hearts with ſuch a Spectacle, as ſhould certainly have the deſired Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, if any ſuch could be wrought: And therefore, cauſes the pretended, tho' Falſly pretended Criminal to be Whipt and Scourged to that degree, that All his Body reſembled but one Ulcer: It was not only Woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but even Harrowed all over; All was Raw, Bloody, nay, even divided piece from piece; and in this Plight
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40936:15"/>does he bring Him forth, expoſes Him to their View, and then bid them look on the MAN, they had ſo grinded their Teeth at. <hi>Ecce Homo; Behold the Man,</hi> that muſt now at leaſt be a greater Object of Pitty, than Hatred. <hi>Conſider now</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>if you can deſire more; if your Cryes be at an end; if this lamentable Spectacle be further worthy your wrath and choller.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he comes a far ſhort in this, as in his former Stratagem; they are ſo far from Relenting, that their Fury becomes more Fiery; their Rage grows ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: And, becauſe he ſtumbles at their Requeſts, they begin to ſtorm and threaten: <hi>Si hunc dimittis non es amicus</hi> Caeſaris; <hi>If thou diſmiſſeſt this Man, thou art no friend of</hi> Caeſars: At which, the Faint-hearted Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour wholly relents; and tho' againſt his Conſcience, againſt a particular Diſſwaſion of his Wife, againſt all the Rules of Honeſty and Worth, gives way, yields to their Deſires, and Delivers up the Priſoner into the hands of the Souldiers; firſt to be treated at their Will and Pleaſure, then to be Crucified.</p>
            <p>The Souldiers have got Him now into their Hands; and, What Souldiers, but the <hi>Romans?</hi> Such as had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes Teſtified, both in Words and Actions, the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Hatred againſt the <hi>Jews.</hi> So that, no Mercy now to be exhibited from ſuch a pack of Hell-Hounds, who with Eyes rowling, Mouths open, Fury in their looks and countenance, Aſſault Him all manner of wayes. His yet crude, and, but at moſt, half-dry'd Wounds, muſt be again laid open by a violent Stripping him of thoſe Garments, which, for a little time, had Defended his torn and ulcerated Fleſh; ſo that now all Bleeds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh, and the Dolour is renew'd, firſt riſing from ſo barbarous a Dilaceration of his Body: But 'tis not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40936:15"/>long to remain in that condition; it muſt be cover'd with a Purple Garment, after the manner of Kings, and great Ones, in Deriſion of what he had aſſerted of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And to carry on the Metaphor to their preſent Satisfaction, tho' to his unſpeakable Torment, they will place a Crown upon his Head, and a Scepter in his Hand; but the Crown, was no other than of Thorns, nay, of ſharpeſt and Iron'd Thorns for hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which was laid on with ſo great violence, that it pierced thro' his Temples, thro' his Scull into his Brains.</p>
            <p>Think deareſt Chriſtians! think what now He Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers in this Condition! What Pangs, what Agonies he muſt feel! Now call to mind his Sweat in the Garden of <hi>Gethſemani,</hi> and tell me, if all this foreſeen, was not a ſufficient, nay, an abundant Cauſe of ſuch a Sweat. If your Fountains of Water be not dried up, your Tears muſt now be viſible. Had you but a Father, Husband, Brother, or any other Friend, but in half ſo Miſerable, ſo Calamitous a Condition; How would you wring your Hands, tear your Hair, pour forth whole Floods of Tears, make your Clamours reach the Heavens, beg, and on your Knees ſtill beg ſome Redreſs, ſome Relief for this your Diſtreſſed Friend? And, Can you do nothing of all this for your Bleeding JESUS? Can you be Eye-Witneſſes unconcern'd, and not bewail the heavy Sighs and Sobs of your fainting SAVIOUR? Can you All ſit here like Rocks unmoved, and ſee the Beſt of Friends, in the moſt Deplorable of Conditions, and that out of pureſt Love for you, and not be ready to ſink down for Grief?</p>
            <p>The Scepter they gave Him in his Hand, was no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a Reed, to expreſs the Floating, and Tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40936:16"/>condition of his Empire: And then thus Clad, thus Crown'd, thus Scepter'd; He muſt be alſo Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renc't and Worſhipt with bended Knee; and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they bent their Knees before Him, Saluting Him with the higheſt of Scorn; <hi>Ave Rex Judaeorum; Hail King of the Jews.</hi> One only Thing could then ſeem wanting, that ſavours Soveraignity, and that is, Exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of Tribute; but that they paid Him in a Smart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Coyn, Multiplying their Blows upon his Crown, to make it ſurer and faſter on his Head.</p>
            <p>Thus Glutted, thus Satiated with their unheard of Cruelty, they go on to Execute the Tyrants Orders. I know there are many Authors ſay, That all this was Acted before his Oſtenſion to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and Diſmiſſion of <hi>Pilate;</hi> and they Found themſelves on St. <hi>John</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; but becauſe St. <hi>Matthew</hi> ſeems to me more full than the other <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> I have traced him in point of <hi>Hiſtory:</hi> And beſides, it leſſens nothing our JESUS Sufferings, whether before or after: For, Whipt he was, Crown'd he was, had a Scepter deliver'd into his Hand; was Saluted on the Knee, and received the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of their hard-hearted Malice on his Head. And then what could remain, but his Faſtning on the Croſs, to put an end unto his Sufferings, the <hi>Jews</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, the Tyranny of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> To which, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might be miſſing, they violently again diveſt him of his Purple Robe, by that means, the third time opening of his Wounds; Cloth him ſlightly with his own Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel; and his now altogether Fainting, and almoſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring Self, do they Load with that unweildy Beam, that heavy Croſs, on which He was to Suffer, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat this Bloody Tragedy. When Loaden, with Kicks, Stripes, Spurns, and other ſuch-like Violences, they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40936:16"/>Force him along; till quite overcome by ſo great a weight he can ſtir no farther, but muſt leave his burthen there, if not aſſiſted: But aſſiſted he ſhall be, tho' with an uncharitable aſſiſtance; for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they loſe their aim, their deſign is ſpoyled, what they all conſpired would fall to the ground. <hi>Simon</hi> therefore the <hi>Cyrenean</hi> coming that way, they ſeize on, and force him to bear the Croſs unto Mount <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vary;</hi> our <hi>Iſaack</hi> walking by that was to be Immolated on it.</p>
            <p>Where being arrived, the Croſs is then laid on the ground; and ſeveral of the Executioners laid violent hands upon this Holocauſt; unmercifully again diſrobe him, fit his Limbs unto the Wood, and with force of Ropes ſtretch them forth to make them anſwer the proportion, and diſtances of the holes they had bor'd before; which done, the doleful and diſmal muſick begins to play; the ſtrokes of the Hammers on the Nailes; and the Nailes thro' the Sacred Hands and Feet of our Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified JESUS: For now I may ſo ſtyle Him, being now faſtned on the Croſs.</p>
            <p>O Bleſſed JESUS! Whatſoever may be the ſentiments of thoſe that put Thee to this Torment; howſoever they may undervalue and vilify Thy Perſon; I adore Thee with all Humility imaginable; and in my thoughts, proſtrate before Thee, tender Thee all the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a Creature, of a Vaſſal, of a Slave. The more vile Thou haſt made Thy Self for my ſake; the greater and fuller in all duty ought to be my return; and therefore with lower ſubmiſſions do I throw my ſelf at the foot of Thy Croſs, whilſt bearing thy Divine Self, then at the Throne of Thy Tryumphant Majeſty in Heaven.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40936:17"/>
            <p>Anatomiſts and Chyrurgeons to whom the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Humane bodyes lie open and diſcover'd, are harmonious in this Truth, that the Nerves and Sinews do more abound, and centre in the Feet and Hands than in any other part of the Body whatſoever. Perforati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons therefore, and all violent Impreſſions muſt be much more quick and ſenſible in thoſe Parts, the Pain much more Intollerable; yet were our Bleſſed JESUS both Hands and Feet pierced, and bor'd thro' with Nailes of ſuch a magnitude, as were able not only to ſecure him to the Wood of the Croſs, but even to bare up and ſupport the weight of all his Body, when erected into the Air: And where the weight of his own Bleſſed Self alwayes preſſing on his Wounds, muſt be a continual widening of them; and ſo every moments renewing of the Torment of the Nailes firſt forcing entry.</p>
            <p>I omit to tell you, how the letting fall of the Croſs into the caſe previouſly made ready in the ground to ſecure its ſtanding firm, could not but be terrible and convulſive of the whole Fabrick, ſhaking all that at once, of which not one part wanted its particular Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And now He is on the Croſs, all bloody, all torn to pieces, a frightful ſpectacle to behold, is he now free from the malice and fury of his Enemies? Nothing leſs. 'Tis true, he is now no more in their hands to be farther buffetted and beaten with either open or clinched fiſts: But they ſtill proſecute him with what weapons they are able to make uſe of. For his greater defamation and reproach, they hang a Thief at each hand of him, and then let flie their envenom'd Tongues againſt Him. What ſcurrilous mocks, and ſarcaſms do they not make uſe of? What jeers, flouts and ſcoffings, do they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40936:17"/>to throw at him? Not ſatisfied with his precedent mockeries and deriſions from the <hi>Jewes</hi> in the Houſe of <hi>Caiphas;</hi> From <hi>Herod</hi> and his Battallions; From <hi>Pilates</hi> Souldiers after his delivery to them, as if nothing had yet paſſed in that kind, they begin a freſh. Firſt the common <hi>Jewes,</hi> with a <hi>Vah, qui deſtruis templum Dei &amp; in triduo aedificas illud, ſalva temetipſum. Thou who deſtroyeſt the Temple of God, and rebuildeſt it in three dayes, ſave thy ſelf.</hi> Again the High Prieſts, <hi>Principes ſacerdotum illudentes cum ſcribis &amp; ſenioribus dicebant, alios ſalvos fecit, ſeipſum non poteſt ſalvum facere. The Princes of the Prieſts illuding with the Scribes and Seni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors ſaid, He has ſaved others, himſelf he cannot ſave.</hi> The very Thieves that hanged with him <hi>Impropera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant ei.</hi> And the <hi>Roman</hi> Souldiers would not be out, <hi>Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debant autem ei &amp; milites.</hi> From all ſorts and degrees he was purſued to his end, who ſuffer'd and died for Perſons of all degrees and conditions.</p>
            <p>Much longer he cannot bare their Calumnies and Injuries, his nature is almoſt ſpent; and a drought from the loſs of ſo much Blood ſeizes him all over, and to ſuch an exceſs, as forced from him, <hi>Sitio, I am thirſty.</hi> He was overcome with a double thirſt; The one Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral in his Body for want of Moiſture: The other yet more Violent in his Soul, by which he thirſted after the Good and Salvation of Mankind. Which thirſt was the occaſion of the other, and of giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his Life; as ſoon after you will hear he did.</p>
            <p>The firſt was but ill Anſwer'd; for inſtead of ſome comfort for his now drooping and decaying Spirits, they give him Gaul a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Vineger to Drink, that his very taſt might not lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> priviledged above his other
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40936:18"/>Sences. But I hope all you here preſent will ſupply the latter; be more grateful unto him, and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to your ſelves. Apply his warm Blood, and ſcatter'd Fleſh unto your Souls; they are all Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign for your Wounds, and no Balſom like to them.</p>
            <p>Having no refreſhment nor recruit of Forces from that bitter Potion; a general failure, and total de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectedneſs of Spirits work on his inferiour part, and makes it cry out; <hi>My God! My God! Why haſt thou deſerted me!</hi> And now even withdrawn thy all-ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting Hand, by the Virtue and Power of which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, I have hitherto with courage run thro' all my now-paſt Sufferings. After which finding an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate diſſolution of his Corporal being coming on, he Publiſhed to the World, he had now drank the <hi>Chalice</hi> his Father gave him, and compleated the Work of Mans Redemption, with a <hi>Conſummatum eſt.</hi> And then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending himſelf to his ſame dear Father, with a <hi>Pater in manus tuas commendo Spiritum meum;</hi> He delivered up the Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>O deareſt <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> art thou gon from us? Haſt thou now left us? Could we not ſecure Thee to our ſelves even faſtned on the Croſs? Our paſt and daily ſins have bin the occaſion of this thy retirement; for our ſins brought Thee from Heaven; caſt Thee into a ſweat of Blood, and then betrayed Thee. Our ſins bound Thee faſt, drag'd Thee along to <hi>Annas,</hi> then <hi>Caiphas</hi> Pallace; there buffetted, beat Thee, and ſpit in Thy Face. Our ſins produced falſe Witneſſes, and gave ſentence of Thy Death. Our ſins farthermore delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Thee into the Hands o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gentiles,</hi> there with reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Crucifigatures preſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>d urged the Execution
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40936:18"/>of the Judgment rendred: Our Sins Scourged, Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Derided Thee: Our Sins ſo Oppreſſed Thee, that Thou couldſt no longer ſupport the heavineſs of the Croſs: Our Sins afterwards nailed Thee faſt on the ſame Croſs; drew upon Thee an exceſſive Drought, and forced that Separation of Soul and Body, we have juſt now taken Notice of.</p>
            <p>But moſt bleſſed and deareſt <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> as our Sins have made Thee for a time with-draw, may our Duty, our Obſervance ſoon bring Thee back again; the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>animate and dumb Creatures have given Us our Leſſon; in their Language they were not ſilent. Pray hearken to St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> behold the Veil of the Temple was rent into pieces, from the top to the bottom; the Earth did quake, the Rocks parted aſunder: But, Did not the Heavens alſo Teſtify their Reſentments? Yes, yes, and that to the Admiration of the World. St. <hi>Luke</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims, for a certainty, That Darkneſs over-ſpread the Face of the Earth, and the <hi>Sun</hi> denyed its Light, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to Expire, at the ſame time, with the <hi>SON</hi> of Juſtice. When Men had loſt all Senſe of what they were doing, the Earth, the Rocks, the Temple, as if burſting with inward Grief, could contain themſelves no longer. The <hi>Sun,</hi> the <hi>Stars</hi> aſhamed at their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, not only hang the Univerſe with the deepeſt Mourning, but cover'd all the Elements with the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and profoundeſt Darkneſs, that they might not be Witneſſes of Mans Actions.</p>
            <p>May our hitherto hardned Hearts, like the Rocks and Temple, burſt aſunder in compliance with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of our now dead <hi>SAVIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R.</hi> May the Old Man of Sin within us, like the Earth, now Tremble to think, he muſt part from, ſo long, and continued a Poſſeſſion;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40936:19"/>let the <hi>SON</hi> that illuminateth every Man coming into this World, ſo Diſpell all inward darkneſs of our Souls, that we may clearly and diſtinctly ſee what He hath ſuffer'd for us, and what He expecteth from us. Let the favourable Influences of Heaven ſo Diſpoſe us, that we may fully Anſwer all his Expectations.</p>
            <p>Think, but think ſeriouſly, if you can do too much for Him that has done ſo much for you. What were all your Lives, tho' I muſt confeſs, you have nothing dearer, and more pretious, if put in Ballance with His? Yet He ſpared it not for you. He prodigally ſpilt his Blood, that He might Purchaſe you a plentiful Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: He abounded in his Mercies, that you might ſee the Fulneſs of his Heart: He has bought you at ſuch a Price, that the World cannot afford the like. Permit not then ſuch a Purchaſe to become void; let not ſuch Mercies be thrown away, nor ſuch a Price be ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Run, run unto his Body, yet hanging on the Croſs; Embrace it with all the Affections of your Souls; Offer up all your Vows; Promiſe to Crucifie Him no more; Conſecrate your ſelves His moſt devoted and faithful Servants from this Moment, and for ever; and you will crown his Sufferings; this his voluntary and frank O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blation of himſelf to Death, with a no leſs joyful than happy Reſurrection.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:40936:19"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of BOOKS, Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Matthew Turner.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Speeches of all the <hi>Prieſts</hi> that Dyed for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Letter to a Baron of <hi>England,</hi> touching his then <hi>Royal-Highneſs.</hi> Folio.</p>
            <p>Tryal of Mr. <hi>David Lewis,</hi> a Jeſuit, and his laſt Speech. <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tryal of Mr. <hi>Francis Johnſon,</hi> a Franciſcan, and his laſt Speech. <hi>Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Abſtract of the Tryal of Sir <hi>Thomas Gaſcoigne,</hi> Fol.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Richard Langhorn's</hi> Memoires, and his laſt Speech. <hi>Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Narrative of the late pretended <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> to the Tune of <hi>Packington's</hi> Pound, Engraved and Repreſented on Copper-Plates, in two Parts.</p>
            <p>Counſels of Wiſdom, or the Maxims of <hi>Solomon:</hi> Done out of <hi>French.</hi> Twelves.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Thoughts for every Day in the Month. <hi>Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-Fours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Papiſt</hi> Miſrepreſented and Repreſented. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Acts of the Clergy of <hi>France.</hi> Quarto.</p>
            <p>An Expoſition of the Doctrine of the <hi>Catholique</hi> Church, by the Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Meaux;</hi> done out of <hi>French. Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon preached before Their Majeſties, on the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation</hi> of the B. V. <hi>Mary,</hi> by <hi>John Betham,</hi> Doctor of <hi>Sorbonne;</hi> Publiſh'd by His Majeſties Command.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
